Chapter 91. The Peekquad meets the rose bud.
Quote, "In vain it was to rake for amber grees in the punch of this Leviathan,
insufferable fetter, denying not inquiry." End quote. Sir T. Brown ve
It was a week or two after the last wailing scene recounted, and when we
were slowly sailing over a sleepy, vapory midday sea, that the many noses
on the Peekquad's deck proved more vigilant discoverers than the three
pairs of eyes aloft. A peculiar and not very pleasant smell was smelt in the sea.
I will bet something now, said Stub, that somewhere hereabouts are some of
those drugged whales we tickled the other day. I thought they would keel up
before long. Presently the vapors in advance slid aside, and there in the
distance lay a ship, whose furled sails be token that some sort of whale must be
alongside. As we glided nearer, the stranger showed French colors from his
peak, and by the eddying cloud of vulture sea fowl that circled and
hovered and swooped around him, it was plain that the whale alongside must be
what the fishermen call a blasted whale, that is, a whale that has died
unmolested on the sea, and so floated an unappropriated corpse. It may well be
conceived what an unsavory odor such a mass must exhale worse than an Assyrian
city in the plague when the living are incompetent to bury the departed. So
intolerable indeed is it regarded by some that no cupity could persuade them
to mour alongside of it. Yet are there those who will still do it,
notwithstanding the fact that the oil obtained from such subjects is of a very
inferior quality, and by no means of the nature of atar of rose.
Coming still nearer with the expiring breeze, we saw that the Frenchman had a
second whale alongside, and this second whale seemed even more of a nose gay
than the first. In truth, it turned out to be one of those problematical whales
that seem to dry up and die with a sort of prodigious dispsia or indigestion,
leaving their defunct bodies almost entirely bankrupt of anything like oil.
Nevertheless, in its proper place we shall see that no knowing fisherman will
ever turn up his nose at such a whale as this, however much he may shun blasted
whales in general.
The Peekquad had now swept so nigh to the stranger that Stub vowed he
recognized his cutting spade pole entangled in the lines that were knotted
round the tail of one of these whales.
"There's a pretty fellow now," he banteringly laughed, standing in the
ship's boughs. "There's a jackal for thee. I well know that these crapos of
Frenchmen are but poor devils in the fishery, sometimes lowering their boats
for breakers, mistaking them for sperm whale spouts. Yes, and sometimes sailing
from their ports with their hold full of boxes of tallow candles and cases of
snuffers for seeing that all the oil they will get won't be enough to dip the
captain's wick into. I We all know these things. But look, yeah, here's a crapo
that is content with our leings. The drugged whale there I mean I and is
content too with scraping the dry bones of that other precious fish she has
there. Poor devil. I say pass round a hat someone and let's make him a present
of a little oil for dear charity's sake.
For what oil he will get from that drugged whale there wouldn't be fit to
burn in a jail. No, not in a condemned cell. And as for the other whale, why,
I'll agree to get more oil by chopping up and trying out these three masts of
ours than he'll get from that bundle of bones. Though, now that I think of it,
it may contain something worth a good deal more than oil. Yes, Amberris.
I wonder now if our old man has thought of that. It's worth trying. Yes, I'm for
it. And so saying, he started for the quarter deck.
By this time the faint air had become a complete calm, so that whether or no,
the Peekquad was now fairly entrapped in the smell, with no hope of escaping
except by its breezing up again. Issuing from the cabin, Stub now called his
boat's crew, and pulled off for the stranger. Drawing across her bow, he
perceived that, in accordance with the fanciful French taste, the upper part of
her stem piece was carved in the likeness of a huge drooping stalk was
painted green, and for thorns had copper spikes projecting from it here and
there, the hole terminating in a symmetrical folded bulb of a bright red
color. Upon her headboards in large guilt letters he read Bhutan de rose
rose button or rose bud and this was the romantic name of this aromatic ship.
Though Stub did not understand the bhutam part of the inscription, yet the
word rose and the bulbous figure head put together sufficiently explained the
whole to him. A wooden rose bud, eh? He cried with his hand to his nose. That
will do very well. But how, like all creation, it smells.
Now, in order to hold direct communication with the people on deck,
he had to pull round the boughs to the starboard side, and thus come close to
the blasted whale, and so talk over it.
Arrived then at this spot, with one hand still to his nose, he balled, "But de
Rose, aoy, are there any of you uh Bhutan de Roses that speak English?"
Yes, rejoined a Gernzie man from the bull works who turned out to be the
chief mate. Well then, uh, my Bhutan de Rosebud. Uh, have you seen the white
whale? What whale? The white whale? A sperm whale? Moby Dick. Have you seen
him? Never heard of such a whale.
Cashelob blanch. White whale. No.
Very good then. Uh, goodbye now and I'll call again in a minute. Then rapidly
pulling back towards the Peekquad and seeing Ahab leaning over the quarter
deck rail awaiting his report, he molded his two hands into a trumpet and
shouted, "No, sir, no!" upon which Ahab retired, and Stub returned to the Frenchman.
He now perceived that the Gernzy man, who had just got into the chains, and
was using a cutting spade, had slung his nose in a sort of bag. "What's the
matter with your nose there?" said Stub.
Broke it. "I wish it were broken, and that I didn't have any nose at all,"
answered the Gernzy man, who did not seem to relish the job he was at very
much. "But what are you holding yours for?" "Oh, uh nothing. It's a wax nose.
I have to hold it on. A fine day, ain't it? Air rather gardeny, I should say.
Throw us a bunch of posies, will you?
Uh, Bhutan de Rose.
What in the devil's name do you want here? roared the Gernseyman, flying into
a sudden passion. Oh, uh, keep cool.
Cool? Yes, that's the word. Uh, why don't you pack those whales in ice while
you're working at them? But uh joking aside though, do you know uh Rosebud
that it's all nonsense trying to get any oil out of such whales? As for that
dried up one there, he has an agill in his whole carcass. I know that well
enough. But do you see the captain here won't believe it? This is his first
voyage. He was a cologne manufacturer before. But come aboard and mayhap he'll
believe you if he won't me. And so I'll get out of this dirty scrape. Anything
to oblige you, my sweet and pleasant fellow, rejoined Stub, and with that he
soon mounted to the deck. There a queer scene presented itself. The sailors, in
tassled caps of red worsted, were getting the heavy tackles in readiness
for the whales, but they worked rather slow and talked very fast, and seemed in
anything but a good humor. all their noses upwardly projected from their
faces like so many jib booms. Now and then pairs of them would drop their work
and run up to the mast head to get some fresh air. Some thinking they would
catch the plague dipped oakum in colar and at intervals held it to their
nostrils. Others having broken the stems of their pipes almost shored off at the
bull were vigorously puffing tobacco smoke so that it constantly filled their alactories.
Stub was struck by a shower of outcries and anathemos proceeding from the
captain's roundhouse a bath and looking in that direction saw a fiery face
thrust from behind the door which was held a jar from within. This was the
tormented surgeon, who after in vain remmonstrating against the proceedings
of the day, had beaken himself to the captain's roundhouse, cabinet, he called
it, to avoid the pest, but still could not help yelling out his intreaties and
indignations at times.
Marking all this, Stub argued well for his scheme, and turning to the
Gernzymen, had a little chat with him, during which the stranger mate,
expressed his detestation of his captain, as a conceited ignoramis, who
had brought them all into so unsavory and unprofitable a pickle. Sounding him
carefully, Stub further perceived that the Gernzy man had not the slightest
suspicion concerning the amberress. He therefore held his peace on that head,
but otherwise was quite frank and confidential with him, so that the two
quickly concocted a little plan for both circumventing and satarizing the
captain, without his at all dreaming of distrusting their sincerity. According
to this little plan of theirs, the Gernzy man, undercover of an
interpreter's office, was to tell the captain what he pleased, but as coming
from Stub, and as for Stub, he was to utter any nonsense that should come
uppermost in him during the interview.
By this time, their destined victim appeared from his cabin. He was a small
and dark but rather delicatel looking man for a sea captain with large
whiskers and mustache however and wore a red cotton velvet vest with watch seals
at his side to this gentleman Stub was now politely introduced by the Gernzy
man who had once ostentatiously put on the aspect of interpreting between them.
"What shall I say to him first?" said he. "Why?" said Stub, eyeing the velvet
vest and watch and seals. You may as well begin by telling him that he looks
a sort of babyish to me, though I don't pretend to be a judge. He says, Msieur,
said the Gernzyman in French, turning to his captain, that only yesterday his
ship spoke a vessel, whose captain and chief mate, with six sailors, had all
died of a fever caught from a blasted whale they had brought alongside.
Upon this the captain started and eagerly desired to know more. What now?
said the Gernzy man to Stub. Why, since he takes it so easy, tell him that now I
have eyed him carefully. I'm quite certain that he's no more fit to command
a whale ship than a St. Jag monkey. In fact, tell him from me he's a baboon. He
vows and declares Msure that the other whale, the dried one, is far more deadly
than the blasted one. In fine Msure, he conjures us, as we value our lives, to
cut loose from these fish.
Instantly the captain ran forward, and in a loud voice commanded his crew to
desist from hoisting the cutting tackles, and at once cast loose the
cables and chains confining the whales to the ship. "What now?" said the Gernzy
man, when the captain had returned to them. "Ah, why, let me see." Yes, you
may as well tell him uh now that uh that
in fact tell him I have diddled him and aside to himself perhaps somebody else.
He says Msure that he's very happy to have been of any service to us. Hearing
this the captain vowed that they were the grateful parties, meaning himself
and mate, and concluded by inviting Stub down into his cabin to drink a bottle of
Bordeaux. He wants you to take a glass of wine with him, said the interpreter.
Thank him hardily. But tell him it's against my principles to drink with the
man I have didd. In fact, tell him I must go. He says Msieur that his
principles won't admit of his drinking.
But that if Msure wants to live another day to drink, then Msure had best drop
all four boats and pulled his ship away from these whales, for it's so calm they won't drift.
By this time Stub was over the side, and getting into his boat hailed the Gernzy
man to this effect. That having a long tow line in his boat, he would do what
he could to help them by pulling out the lighter whale of the two from the ship's
side. While the Frenchman's boats then were engaged in towing the ship one way,
Stub benevolently towed away at his whale the other way, ostentatiously
slacking out a most unusually long tow line. Presently a breeze sprang up. Stub
feained to cast off from the whale.
Hoisting his boats, the Frenchman soon increased his distance, while the
Peekquad slid in between him and Stub's whale, whereupon Stub quickly pulled to
the floating body, and hailing the Peekquad to give notice of his
intentions, at once proceeded to reap the fruit of his unrighteous cunning.
Seizing his sharp boat spade, he commenced an excavation in the body, a
little behind the side fin. You would almost have thought he was digging a
cellar there in the sea, and when at length his spade struck against the
gaunt ribs, it was like turning up old Roman tiles and pottery buried in fat
English lom. His boat's crew were all in high excitement, eagerly helping their
chief, and looking as anxious as gold hunters, and all the time numberless fowls were
diving and ducking and screaming and yelling and fighting around them. Stub
was beginning to look disappointed, especially as the horrible nose gay
increased, when suddenly, from out the very heart of this plague, there stole a
faint stream of perfume which flowed through the tide of bad smells without
being absorbed by it, as one river will flow into and then along with another
without at all blending with it for a time. I have it. I have it," cried Stub
with delight, striking something in the subterranean regions. "A purse! A
purse!" Dropping his spade, he thrust both hands in, and drew out handfuls of
something that looked like ripe Windsor soap, or rich modeled old cheese, very
anxious and savory with all. You might easily dent it with your thumb. It is of
a hue between yellow and ash color. And this, good friends, is amberress, worth
a gold guinean ounce to any drugist.
Some six handfuls were obtained, but more was unavoidably lost in the sea,
and still more perhaps might have been secured were it not for impatient Ahab's
loud command to stub, to desist, and come on board, else the ship would bid them goodbye.